Chapter 119.
The candles.
Warmest climbs but nurse the crulest fangs. The tiger of Bengal crouches in
spiced groves of ceaseless vir. Skies the most eulgent but basket the
deadliest thunders. Gorgeous Cuba knows tornadoes that never swept tame northern
lands. So too is it that in these respplendant Japanese seas the mariner
encounters the direest of all storms, the typhoon. It will sometimes burst out
of that cloudless sky like an exploding bomb upon a dazed and sleepy town.
Towards evening of that day, the Peekquad was torn of her canvas, and
bare pold was left to fight a typhoon which had struck her directly ahead.
When darkness came on, sky and sea roared and split with the thunder and
blazed with the lightning that showed the disabled mass fluttering here and
there with the rags which the first fury of the tempest had left for its after
sport. Holding by a shroud, Starbucks was standing on the quarter deck at
every flash of the lightning, glancing aloft to see what additional disaster
might have befallen the intricate hamper there, while Stub and Flask were
directing the men in the higher hoisting and firmer lashing of the boats. But all
their pains seemed not. Though lifted to the very top of the cranes, the windward
quarterboat Ahabs, did not escape. A great rolling sea dashing high up
against the reeling ship's high teetering side stove in the boat's
bottom at the stern and left it again all dripping through like a sieve.
Bad work, bad work, Mr. Starbucks, said Stub, regarding the wreck. But the sea
will have its way. Stub, for one, can't fight it. You see, Mr. Starbucks, a wave
has such a great long start before it leaps. All around the world it runs and
then comes the spring. But as for me, all the start I have to meet it is just
across the deck here. But never mind, it's all in fun. So the old song says,
sings, "Oh, jolly is the gale and a joker is the whale, a flourish in his
tail. Such a funny, sporty, gy, jesty, jokey, hokeyp pokey lad is the ocean.
The scuttle of flying, that's his fliponly fman when he stirs in the
spicing. Such a funny, sporty, gy, justesty, jokey, hokeyp pokey lad is the
ocean. No. Thunder splits the ship, but he only smacks his lips. A tasting of
this flip. Such a funny, sporty, gy, justesty, jokey, hokeyp pokey lad is the
ocean. Oh, a vast stub, cried Starbucks.
Let the typhoon sing and strike his harp here in our rigging. But if thou art a
brave man, thou wilt hold thy peace. But I'm not a brave man. Never said I was a
brave man. I am a coward, and I sing to keep up my spirits. And I'll tell you
what it is, Mr. Starbucks. There's no way to stop my singing in this world,
but to cut my throat. And when that's done, 10 to one, I sing you the doxology
for a windup. Mad man, look through my eyes if thou hast none of thine own.
What? How can you see better of a dark night than anybody else? Never mind how
foolish. Here, cried Starbucks, seizing Stub by the shoulder, and pointing his
hand towards the weather bow. Marks thou not that the gale comes from the
eastward? The very course Ahab is to run from Moby Dick, the very course he swung
to this day noon. Now mark his boat there. Where is that stove? In the stern
sheets, man. Where he is want to stand.
His standpoint is stove man. Now jump overboard and sing away if thou must.
I don't hath understand ye. What's in the wind?
Yes. Yes. Round the cape of good hope is the shortest way to Nantucket. Siloquis
Starbucks suddenly heededless of Stub's question. The gale that now hammers at
us to save us. We can turn it into a fair wind that will drive us towards
home. Yonder to windward is all blackness of doom. But to lured
homeward, I see it lightens up there, but not with the lightning. At that
moment, in one of the intervals of profound darkness, following the
flashes, a voice was heard at his side, and almost at the same instant a volley
of thunder peels rolled overhead. Who's there? Old thunder, said Ahab, groping
his way along the bull works to his pivot hole, but suddenly finding his
path made plain to him by elbowed lances of fire.
Now, as the lightning rod to aspire on shore is intended to carry off the
perilous fluid into the soil, so the kindred rod, which at sea some ships
carry to each mast, is intended to conduct it into the water. But as this
conductor must descend to considerable depth, that its end may avoid all
contact with the hull, and as moreover, if kept constantly towing there, it
would be liable to many mishaps, besides interfering not a little, with some of
the rigging, and more or less impeding the vessel's way in the water. Because
of all this, the lower parts of a ship's lightning rods are not always overboard,
but are generally made in long, slender links, so as to be the more readily
hauled up into the chains outside, or thrown down into the sea, as occasion
may require. "The rods! The rods!" cried Starbucks to the crew, suddenly
admonished vigilance by the vivid lightning that had just been darting
Flambo to light Ahab to his post. "Are they overboard? Drop them over for and
aft quick. I've asked cried Ahab. Let's have fair play here, though we be the
weaker side. Yet I'll contribute to raise rods on the Himalayas and Andes
that all the world may be secured but out on privileges. Let them be, sir.
Look a loft, cried Starbucks. The Corpusance. The Corpusance.
All the yard arms were tipped with a pallet fire, and touched at each
triointed lightning rod end with three tapering white flames. Each of the three
tall masss was silently burning in that sulfurous air, like three gigantic wax
tapers before an altar. "Last the boat!
Let it go!" cried Stub at this instant, as a swashing sea heaved up under his
own little craft, so that its gunnel violently jammed his hand as he was
passing a lashing. Blast it. But slipping backwards on the deck, his
uplifted eyes caught the flames, and immediately shifting his tone, he cried,
"The Corpus ants, have mercy on us all."
To sailors, oaths are household words.
They will swear in the trance of the calm and in the teeth of the tempest.
They will imprecate curses from the top sail yard arms when most they teeter
over to a sthing sea. But in all my voyagings seldom have I heard a common
oath when God's burning finger has been laid upon the ship when his minupars
has been woven into the shrouds in the cordage. While this paladness was
burning a loft, few words were heard from the enchanted crew, who in one
thick cluster stood on the folks, all their eyes gleaming in that pale
phosphoresence like a faraway constellation of stars. Relieved against
the ghostly light, the gigantic jet negro Dagu loomed up to thrice his real
stature, and seemed the black cloud from which the thunder had come. The parted
mouth of Tashtega revealed his shark white teeth, which strangely gleamed as
if they too had been tipped by corpusants, while lit up by the
prednatural light, Que's tattooing burned like satanic blue flames on his
body. The tableau all waned at last with the paladness aloft, and once more the
Peekquad and every soul on her decks were wrapped in a paw. A moment or two
passed when Starbucks going forward pushed against someone. It was Stub.
What think thou now, man? I heard thy cry. It was not the same in the song.
No, it wasn't. I said, the corpusants have mercy on us all, and I hope they
will still. But do they only have mercy on long faces? Have they no bowels for a
laugh? And look you, Mr. Starbucks, but it's too dark for a look. Hear me then.
I take that mast head flame we saw for a sign of good luck. For those masts are
rooted in a hold that is going to be choa block with sperm oil, do you see?
And so all that sperm oil will work up into the mass like sap in a tree. Yes,
our three mass will yet be as three spermaceti candles. That's the good
promise we saw. At that moment, Starbucks caught sight of Stub's face
slowly beginning to glimmer into sight.
Glancing upwards, he cried, "See, see."
And once more the high, tapering flames were beheld with what seemed redoubled
supernaturalness in their power. "The Corpusons, have mercy on us all," cried Stub again.
At the base of the main mast, full beneath the dloon and the flame, the
parsy was kneeling in Ahab's front, but with his head bowed away from him, while
nearby, from the arched and overhanging rigging, where they had just been
engaged in securing a spar, a number of the seammen, arrested by the glare, now
cohered together, and hung pendulus like a knot of numbed wasps from a drooping
orchard twig, in various enchanted attitudes, like the standing ing or
stepping or running skeletons in Herculanium. Others remained rooted to
the deck, but all their eyes upcast.
I, I man, cried Ahab. Look up at it.
Mark it well. The white flame but lights the way to the white whale. Hand me
those main mass links there. I would fain feel this pulse and let mine beat
against it. Blood against fire. So then turning the last link held fast in his
left hand, he put his foot upon the parse, and with fixed upward eye, and
high-flung right arm, he stood erect before the lofty triointed trinity of flames.
Oh, thou clear spirit of clear fire, whom on these seas I, as Persian once
did worship, till in the sacramental act so burned by thee, that to this hour I
bear the scar. I now know thee, thou clear spirit, and I now know that thy
right worship is defiance, to neither love nor reverence wilt thou be kind.
And even for hate thou canst but kill, and all are killed. No fearless fool now
fronts thee. I own thy speechless placeless power, but to the last gasp of
my earthquake life will dispute its unconditional, unintegral mastery in me.
In the midst of the personified impersonal, a personality stands here.
Though but a point at best, whensoever I came, whensoever I go, yet while I
earthly live, the queenly personality lives in me and feels her royal rights.
But war is pain, and hate is woe. Come in thy lowest form of love, and I will
kneel and kiss thee. But at thy highest come as mere suppernal power. And though
thou launchest navies of full freighted worlds, there's that in here that still
remains indifferent. Oh thou clear spirit of thy fire thou madeest me, and
like a true child of fire, I breathe it back to thee.
Sudden repeated flashes of lightning, the nine flames leap lengthwise to
thrice their previous height. Ahab with the rest closes his eyes, his right hand
pressed hard upon them.
I own thy speechless, placeless power.
Said I not so. Nor was it rung from me, nor do I now drop these links. Thou
canst blind, but I can then grope. Thou canst consume, but I can then be ashes.
Take the homage of these poor eyes and shutter hands. I would not take it. The
lightning flashes through my skull. Mine eyeballs ache and ache. My whole beaten
brain seems as beheaded and rolling on some stunning ground. Oh. Oh. Yet
blindfold yet will I talk to thee. Light though thou be. Thou leapest out of
darkness. But I am darkness leaping out of light. Leaping out of thee. The
javelins cease. Open eyes. See or not.
There burn the flames. Oh, thou magnanimous. Now I do glory in my genealogy.
But thou art but my fiery father. My sweet mother I know not. Oh cruel, what
hast thou done with her? There lies my puzzle, but thine is greater. Thou
knowest not how came ye, hence callest thyself unbegotten. certainly knowest
not thy beginning, hence callst thyself unbegun. I know that of me, which thou
knowest not of thyself, oh thou omnipotent. There is some unsuffing
thing beyond thee, thou clear spirit, to whom all thy eternity is but time, all
thy creativeness mechanical.
Through thee, thy flaming self, my scorched eyes do dimly see it. Oh thou
foundling fire, thou hermit immemorial.
Thou too hast thy incommunicable riddle, thy unparticipated grief. Here again
with haughty agony I read my sire. Leap, leap up and lick the sky. I leap with
thee. I burn with thee. Would fain be welded with thee. Defyingly I worship thee.
The boat. The boat!" cried Starbug.
"Look at thy boat, old man."
Ahab's harpoon, the one forged at Perth's fire, remained firmly lashed in
its conspicuous crotch, so that it projected beyond his whaleboat's bow.
But the sea that had stow its bottom had caused the loose leather sheath to drop
off, and from the keen steel barb there now came a leveled flame of pale forked
fire. As the silent harpoon burned there like a serpent's tongue, Starbucks
grasped Ahab by the arm. God, God is against the old man. Forbear, it is an
ill voyage, ill begun, ill continued.
Let me square the yards while we may, old man, and make a fair wind of it
homewards, to go on a better voyage than this. Overhearing Starbucks, the
panic-stricken crew instantly ran to the braces, though not a sail was left
aloft. For the moment all the agast mates thoughts seemed theirs, they
raised a half mutinous cry. But dashing the rattling lightning links to the
deck, and snatching the burning harpoon, Ahab waved it like a torch among them,
swearing to transfix with it the first sailor that but cast loose a rope's end.
Petrified by his aspect, and still more shrinking from the fiery dart that he
held, the men fell back in dismay, and Ahab again spoke.
All your oaths to hunt the white whale are as binding as mine, and heart, soul,
and body, lungs, and life, old Ahab, is bound. And that you may know to what
tune this heart beats, look you here.
Thus I blow out the last fear. And with one blast of his breath he extinguished the flame.
As in the hurricane that sweeps the plane men fly the neighborhood of some
lone gigantic elm whose very height and strength but render it so much the more
unsafe, because so much the more a mark for thunderbolts. So at those last words
of Ahabs, many of the mariners did run from him in a terror of dismay.